Guide to the Olive Tilford Dargan and Rose Pastor Stokes Correspondence TAM.110
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Olive Tilford Dargan and Rose Pastor Stokes Correspondence
1917-1931
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dargan, Olive Tilford, 1869-1968
Zipser, Arthur
Zipser, Pearl
TAM.110
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
Olive Tilford Dargan (1869-1968), was an Appalachian poet and novelist. Under the pseudonym Fielding Burke, she wrote two novels about the Gastonia, North Carolina textile workers' strike of 1929, Call Home the Heart (1932) and A Stone Came Rolling (1935). Rose Pastor Stokes (1879-1933) was a widely published socialist and communist, and author of proletarian plays and poetry. Born in Russian Poland in 1879, Stokes immigrated to the United States where she worked in a cigar factory. In 1903 she became an assistant to the editor of the Jewish Daily News in New York. In 1905 she married James Graham Phelps Stokes, a wealthy socialist and reformer. In 1918 she was sentenced to ten years in prison under the Espionage Act but the conviction was overturned on appeal. During this period she became a member of the Communist Party and in 1922 was a delegate to the Fourth Congress of the Communist International in Moscow. In 1925 she and James were divorced and two years later she married Jerome Isaac Romaine. She died in 1933 of cancer. The collection contains forty-one letters from Olive Tilford Dargan to Rose Pastor Stokes, two letters from Stokes to Dargan, a letter from the Tallahassee Power Company regarding the possibility of a reservoir covering some property owned by Dargan, and a telegram to Dargan from "John and Mary." The letters between Dargan and Stokes are largely personal in nature, and indicate a close friendship. There is also some discussion of literary and political matters, and the letters from 1930-1931 are concerned with Stoke's final illness.
Custodial History
Arthur and Pearl Zipser sent a gift of Olive Tilford Dargan's correspondence in 1990. The accession number associated with this gift is 1990.006. The letters may have been given to Arthur and Pearl Zipser by Cecil Befrage, who in turn had received them from J. J. Jerome.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Olive Tilford Dargan (1869-1968), was an Appalachian poet and novelist, who lived in North Carolina from 1906 until her death. Under the pseudonym Fielding Burke, she wrote two novels about the Gastonia, North Carolina textile workers' strike of 1929, Call Home the Heart (1932) and A Stone Came Rolling (1935). Rose Pastor Stokes (1879-1933) was widely published socialist and communist. Born in Russian Poland in 1879, Stokes immigrated in 1882 to England and in 1890 to the United States where she worked in a cigar factory. In 1903 she became an assistant to the editor of the Jewish Daily News in New York. In 1905 she married James Graham Phelps Stokes, a wealthy socialist and reformer. By 1912 Stokes was an active socialist participating in labor actions in New York City and writing proletarian poetry and plays, including The Woman Who Wouldn't (1916). In 1918 she was sentenced to ten years in prison under the Espionage Act but the conviction was overturned on appeal in 1921. During this period she became a member of the Communist Party and in 1922 was an American delegate to the Fourth Congress of the Communist International in Moscow. In 1925 she and James were divorced and two years later she married Jerome Isaac Romaine. She died in 1933 of cancer in Germany, where she had sought treatment. I Belong to the Working Class: The Unfinished Autobiography of Rose Pastor Stokes, was published in 1992.
Scope and Content Note
Contains forty-one letters from Olive Tilford Dargan to Rose Pastor Stokes, two letters from Stokes to Dargan, a letter from the Tallahassee Power Company regarding the possibility of a reservoir covering some property owned by Dargan, and a telegram to Dargan from "John and Mary." Dargan's letters to Stokes (and Stokes's two letters to Dargan) are largely personal in nature, and indicate a close friendship. There is also some discussion of literary and political matters, and the letters from 1930-1931 are concerned with Stokes's final illness.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes
Related Material
Olive Tilford Dargan Papers, University of Kentucky.
Rose Pastor Stokes Papers (TAM 053)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Pearl and Arthur Zipser, 1990. The accession number associated with this gift is 1990.006.
Correspondence.; Feminists -- United States.; Female friendship |z United States.; Women communists -- United States.; Women poets, American.; Women socialists -- United States.; Women novelists, American.; Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933; Tallahassee Power Company; Zipser, Arthur; Zipser, Pearl
- Series I: Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes, ca. 1917-1931.
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (2), ca.1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Rose Pastor Stokes, ca.1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stokes, Letters to Olive Tilford Dargan (2), undated, Dec 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (14), 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John and Mary: Telegram to Olive Tilford Dargan, Jul 19, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tallahassee Power Company: Letter to Olive Tilford Dargan, plus Clipping, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Rose Pastor Stokes, Feb 21, ca. 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (7), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (10), plus one telegram, one postcard, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (2), ca.1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes (4), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photocopies (Box 2)